♪No matter how far the road is, don’t be afraid♪
♪无论路有多远，都不要害怕♪
♪Love is as gentle as longing ♪
♪爱像渴望一样温柔 ♪
♪The scars will definitely scab♪
♪伤痕一定会结痂♪
♪Funds become the flower of time♪
♪资金成为时间之花♪
♪Eventually someone will quote it for you♪
♪最终 会有人为你引用♪
♪Keep going, you won’t be alone♪
♪继续前进， 你不会孤单♪
♪Dialogue with the times♪
♪与时代对话♪
♪The light of response falls gently♪
♪响应之光轻轻落下♪
♪May you have him in your world♪
♪愿你的人海有他♪
♪Happiness like green tea and rooftops♪
♪像绿茶和屋顶一样的幸福♪
♪You know, life is full of regrets♪
♪你知道，人生充满 遗憾♪
♪Masih menu♪
♪马西赫菜单♪
♪Winter and summer♪
♪冬天和夏天♪
[Panakea Cinta] [Vol. 10]
[Panakea Cinta] [第 10 集]
[2022 Sichuan Provincial Literature and Art Project Funded Works]
【 2022年四川省文学艺术项目资助作品】
[Adapted from the lemon language novel "Panakea Cinta"]
【改编自 柠檬语言小说《Panakea Cinta》】
slower.
慢一点。
Slow down, Fang Mingfan.
慢点，方明凡。
This is a mountain road.
这是一条山路。
scared?
害怕的？
I'm not afraid.
我不害怕。
You still want to go with me.
你还想跟我一起去。
If something happens to us,
如果 我们出了什么事，
How can we save Vian and the Doctor? Gu?
我们该如何 拯救维安和博士呢？顾？
If you follow our very slow pace...
如果你按照我们 非常慢的速度...
slower.
慢一点。
We thought it would be nice if we could arrive before dawn.
我们想如果我们能在黎明前到达就好了。
What should we do?
我们应该做什么？
Their cell phones must be out of battery.
他们的手机 肯定没电了。
I called them earlier but that also failed.
我早些时候给他们打电话， 但也失败了。
cannot.
不能。
The young boss never gave up on me.
年轻的老板从来没有 放弃过我。
I can't live without him either.
我也离不开他。
What does "give up on you" mean?
“放弃你”是什么意思？
Why should I give up on you?
为什么要放弃你？
Didn't you ask?
你没问吗？
What is the mortality rate for the surgery I have ?
我进行的手术的死亡率是多少 ？
I said before that I didn't record.
之前我说过我没有录音。
In fact, during my first surgery...
事实上，在 我的第一次手术中...
The patient died on the operating table.
病人死 在手术台上。
That night...
那晚...
The patient's vital signs are unstable.
病人的生命体征不稳定。
Blood pressure 82/48 mmHg.
血压82/48毫米汞柱。
Blood oxygen saturation is 70%.
血氧饱和度70%。
This is a blood blister aneurysm.
这是血泡动脉瘤。
Bleeding spots must be treated immediately.
出血点必须 立即治疗。
How long until the Doctor arrives?
距离博士还有多久 他来了吗？
PhD. He still has diarrhea.
博士。他仍然腹泻。
Director Zhang is also performing another operation.
张主任还在 进行另一项手术。
Blood oxygen saturation is below 70%.
血氧饱和度 低于70%。
The amount of bleeding has exceeded 1000 ml.
出血量已超过1000毫升。
Can't wait any longer.
不能再等了。
Perform surgery immediately.
立即进行手术。
PhD. He just asked you
博士。他只是问你
Maintain patient's vital signs.
维持患者的生命体征。
If you operate now,
如果你现在操作，
You must take responsibility for this operation.
你必须 对这个手术负责。
Blood vesicle aneurysm.
血泡动脉瘤。
This is the most difficult and risky surgery .
这是难度最大、风险最大的手术 。
Can you do it?
你可以做到吗？
if i don't try
如果我不尝试的话
He will definitely die.
他一定会死。
Perform surgery immediately.
立即进行手术。
Absorbent gelatin sponge.
吸收性明胶海绵。
The patient was in shock and required immediate blood transfusion.
患者处于休克状态， 需要立即输血。
The patient's heart stopped.
病人的心跳停止了。
Perform cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) immediately.
立即进行心肺复苏 (CPR)。
PhD. It's funny if he doesn't come
博士。他不来很有趣
The patient is dying,
病人快要死了，
what can I do?
我能做些什么？
Don't you want me to let him die?
你不想让我让他死吗？
You only had surgery.
你只做过手术。
Never had aneurysm surgery.
从未做过 动脉瘤手术。
How can you do this without permission?
未经许可你怎么能这样做？
Fortunately, the patient's family members are reasonable and do not blame you.
还好患者家属 通情达理，没有怪罪你。
Take a good look at yourself.
你好好审视一下自己。
No matter what you say, he can't even deal with an aneurysm.
不管你说什么，他 连动脉瘤都对付不了。
How dare he perform surgery without waiting for the attending doctor.
他怎么敢不等主治医生就做手术。
Why should he perform well?
他为什么要表现出色？
PhD. He said that some people
博士。他说，有些人
No talent. Just become a surgeon.
没有天赋 直接成为一名外科医生。
I think in our unit,
我想在我们单位，
No medical team dared to admit him.
没有医疗队 敢接收他。
(Try what you say, he can't even handle an aneurysm.)
（试试你说的，他甚至无法 处理动脉瘤。）
(How dare he perform surgery without waiting for the attending doctor.)
（他怎么敢不等主治医生就做手术。）
(Why does he have to act so well?)
（为什么他要演得这么厉害？）
(Dr. He said that some people)
（何博士说，有些人）
(There is no natural talent for being a direct surgeon .)
（没有成为一名直接外科医生的天赋 。）
(I think in our unit,)
（我想在我们单位，）
(No medical team dares to admit him now .)
（现在没有医疗队 敢接收他了。）
(You only had surgery.)
（您只接受过手术。）
( Aneurysm surgery has never been performed .)
（从未进行过 动脉瘤手术。）
(How can you do this without permission?)
（未经允许怎么可以 这样做？）
(Fortunately, the patient’s family members are reasonable and don’t blame you.)
（还好患者家属 通情达理，不怪你。）
(Take a good look at yourself.)
（你好好审视一下自己。）
(Try what you say, he can't even handle an aneurysm.)
（试试你说的，他甚至无法 处理动脉瘤。）
(How dare he perform surgery without waiting for the attending doctor.)
（他怎么敢不等主治医生就做手术。）
(Why does he have to act so well?)
（为什么他要演得这么厉害？）
(Why did he die?)
（他为什么死？）
At that time everyone thought my career was over,
当时大家都以为 我的职业生涯结束了，
Including myself.
包括我自己。
So, dr. Can I help you in the future?
所以，博士。顾以后帮你吗？
Do you know why I keep calling him little boss?
你知道我为什么 一直叫他小老板吗？
He's only two levels above me.
他只比我高两级。
But he and I are completely opposite people.
但我和他是完全相反的人。
His first surgery made him famous.
他的第一次手术 使他出名。
Presided over thalamic tumor surgery when he was young
年轻时主持丘脑肿瘤手术
Become a legend in the Neurosurgery Department of Huaren Hospital.
成为 华仁医院神经外科的传奇人物。
I just don't think so
我只是不这么认为
He will tell useless people
他会告诉无用的人
So that everyone ignored it,
以至于大家都忽略了，
About to resign and change fields...
即将辞职 并改变领域...
"You're unhappy."
“你不高兴了。”
"I need an assistant."
“我需要一个助手。”
Fang Mingfan.
Fang Mingfan.
why are you back
你为什么回来了
What?
什么？
I mean since you have decided to give up
我的意思是 既然你 已经决定放弃
Why are you still coming to the hospital?
你怎么还来医院？
I am used to it.
我习惯了。
Maybe this is also instinct.
也许这也是本能吧。
Fang Mingfan.
Fang Mingfan.
Regarding transnasal sphenoidal approach to pituitary tumor surgery,
关于经鼻蝶入路垂体瘤手术，
How much do you understand
你明白多少
I used to study video
我以前是学视频的
And have seen some lecturers do this.
并看到 一些讲师这样做。
So, I'm sorry to upset you.
所以，很抱歉让你感到不安。
I need a senior assistant.
我需要一名高级助理。
I can.
我可以。
Then the little boss also came to help with the charity work here.
然后小老板 也来帮忙这里的慈善工作。
I don't want it either
我也不想要
Face those who point fingers at China.
面对那些 对中国指手画脚的人。
So, I followed him here.
于是，我就跟着他来到了这里。
So from that point on, Dr. Gu,
所以从那时起，博士。顾,
From a senior boss to a young boss?
从资深老板变 年轻老板？
So, why is he so partial to you?
那么，他为什么 对你这么偏心呢？
I once asked him why he chose me.
我曾经问过他为什么选择我。
He is not partial.
他并不偏心。
He said he didn't want to see defectors.
他说他不想看到 叛逃者。
He doesn't like defectors.
他不喜欢叛逃者。
after that?
在那之后？
When will you start again?
你什么时候 重新开始？
Second surgery?
第二次手术？
I'm not ready yet.
我还没准备好。
I know I'm useless.
我知道我没用。
Do not say.
不要说。
You are useless, not as bad as me.
你没用，还不如我坏。
If you are not ready yet,
如果你还没有准备好，
So it takes time to prepare.
所以需要时间准备。
Life is so long, there will definitely be a next time.
人生那么长， 肯定还会有下一次。
There will definitely be a next time.
肯定还会有下次的。
I think the mobile charity clinic is just ahead,
我觉得流动慈善诊所 就在前方，
We are here waiting for them.
我们在这里等他们。
Wait until it gets a little lighter before continuing the search.
等到天稍微亮一点 再继续搜寻。
Mali.
马里。
Be careful.
当心。
May I?
可以吗？
I have nothing.
我什么都没有。
Gu Yunzheng.
Gu Yunzheng.
Bangun, Gu Yunzheng.
Bangun, Gu Yunzheng.
Don't fall asleep.
别睡着了。
Don't worry.
不用担心。
I didn't pass out.
我没有昏倒。
I'm just sleepy.
我只是困了。
Doing charity therapy all day
一整天都在做慈善治疗
The road is so long.
路又那么长。
Really tired.
真的累了。
If you feel uncomfortable,
如果你感觉不舒服，
must tell me yes
必须告诉我是的
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
to be honest,
说实话，
I'm glad you took care of me.
我很高兴你照顾我。
so,
所以，
If you feel uncomfortable,
如果你感觉不舒服，
I'll just say it.
我就直接说吧。
Rest first.
先休息吧。
This cannot go on.
不能再这样下去了。
I went to the rescuers.
我去找救援人员。
wait for me here.
你在这里等我。
Be careful, Su Wei'an.
小心点，苏危安。
quickly.
快速地。
hurry up.
快点。
Situ.
司徒。
Gu Yunzheng.
Gu Yunzheng.
wake up.
醒来。
I was shocked.
我感到震惊。
You are really strong.
你真的很强。
How are you?
你还好吗？
I really don't want to wake up.
我真的不想醒来。
If only you'd wake me up in two seconds
要是你两秒后叫醒我就好了
i can kiss you
我可以吻你
so far.
到目前为止。
Next time if you have this kind of dream again, don't involve me anymore.
下次你要是再做 这种梦，就别再牵涉到我了。
how?
如何？
You are busy with everything,
你什么事都忙，
Get ready to get busy again and figure out other people's dreams.
准备好再次忙于找出 其他人的梦想。
Wei'an.
Wei'an.
quickly.
快速地。
Please carry him inside.
请把他抬进去。
What happened to the young boss?
年轻的老板怎么了？
what happen?
发生什么事？
What’s wrong with you?
你怎么了？
【Friendly Hospital】
【友好医院】
you're awake.
你醒了。
How do you feel now?
你现在感觉怎么样？
Thirsty.
口渴。
Drink water first.
先喝水。
Drinking plenty of water can boost your metabolism.
喝大量的水 可以促进新陈代谢。
hungry.
饥饿的。
Do you want to eat porridge?
你想吃粥吗？
Unable to wake up.
无法醒来。
It doesn't matter. I don't want to eat it.
没关系。我不想吃它。
I bribe you.
我贿赂你。
Mali.
马里。
You picked me up.
你接我了。
am I wrong?
我错了吗？
Wei'an sedang suap Dr. Gu.
Wei'an sedang suap Dr. Gu.
both of them
他们两个
What to do in Kampung Rabe at night ?
甘榜拉贝 (Kampung Rabe)晚上做什么 ？
Vian looked like a different person.
维安看起来就像 变了一个人。
PhD. me too.
博士。我也一样。
While in the village, they would not
在村里的时候，他们不会
eat any kind of fruit
吃任何种类的水果
Will it be poisoned like this?
会中毒成这样吗？
Good morning, Sister Lan.
早上好，兰姐。
Why are you making a video call to your mom?
你为什么要给 妈妈打视频电话？
I'm already late for dancing in the square.
我 去广场跳舞已经迟到了。
Square dance?
广场舞？
Isn’t it Beijing time now?
现在不是北京时间吗
Is it only eight o'clock in the morning?
现在才早上八点吗？
Workers don’t even get up that early.
工人们甚至不会那么早起床。
Well, I chatted with you for a while.
嗯，我 和你聊了一会儿。
wrong.
不对。
Today is the weekend,
今天是周末，
You're just sitting in the hospital.
你就坐在医院里。
If there is no class, you take a test.
如果没有课， 你就做一个测试。
At least, go to the library and sit.
至少， 去图书馆坐坐吧。
You came to France in vain,
你徒劳地来到法国，
I don’t want to just enjoy life.
我不想直接享受生活。
Who said I am in the hospital every day?
谁说我 每天都在医院？
Last week, I went to the village for a charity therapy session.
上周，我去 村里进行了一次慈善治疗。
Feel the experience and atmosphere of the French countryside
感受法国乡村的体验和氛围
and the customs and habits of the local people.
以及当地人的风俗习惯。
You treat villagers instead of going to the hospital,
你给村民治病 而不是去医院，
There is no difference.
没有任何区别。
You see, your skin has darkened.
你看，你的皮肤已经黑了。
Women must be good at taking care of their skin.
女人一定要善于保养自己的皮肤。
Take a look, what is this?
看看这是什么？
Sun protection.
防晒。
Spray every two hours.
每两小时喷洒一次。
I'm telling you, don't be so stingy.
我告诉你， 别这么小气。
Cheaper than future whitening injections.
比以后打美白针要便宜。
Yes I know.
是的，我知道。
I don't go to charity therapy every day .
我并不是每天都 去接受慈善治疗。
I'm not exposed to the sun every day.
我不是 每天都暴露在阳光下。
So, why does the skin turn dark?
那么，皮肤为什么会变黑呢？
run out,
用完，
It should be caused by age factor.
应该是年龄因素造成的。
There is something wrong with your metabolism.
你的新陈代谢有问题。
metabolism?
代谢？
I'm not even 30 yet.
我还不到 30岁。
Until my heart said this to my son.
直到我的心对我的儿子这么说。
You don’t compare with me.
你不跟我比。
My genes are so good
我的基因太好了
Every time we go out,
每次我们出去，
People always say we are like brothers and sisters.
人们总是说 我们就像兄弟姐妹。
Who has such poor eyesight?
谁的视力这么差？
Come on, what's the matter?
快点啊，有什么事吗？
there is nothing.
没有什么。
I miss my mother.
我想念妈妈。
When I go to charity therapy
当我去接受慈善治疗时
i saw a girl
我看到一个女孩
He only lives with his mother
他只和他的母亲住在一起
So I suddenly missed my mother.
所以我突然想妈妈了。
Do you still have time to miss me?
你还有时间想念我吗？
I mean, you have a lot of time.
我的意思是，你有很多时间。
You don't have a boyfriend, right?
你没有男朋友吧？
Every time I talk to my mother
每次和妈妈说话
We will end up discussing the same topic.
我们最后会讨论同一个话题。
Why don't you ask me?
你为什么不问我？
Is it difficult or not difficult to travel abroad?
坐国外难还是不难？
You are the one who is looking for this article.
您就是正在寻找这篇文章的人。
I gave birth to you and you are so beautiful.
我生下了你，你是如此美丽。
i don't want you
我不想要你
Face test equipment every day.
每天面对测试设备。
You know what people call this?
你知道人们怎么称呼这个吗？
What a waste of beautiful youth.
浪费了美好的青春年华。
OK
好的。
Mom wins.
妈妈赢了。
I am an open-minded mother.
我是一个思想开放的母亲。
I just want you to feel loved.
我只是想让你 感受到爱。
It doesn't matter what the result is.
结果是什么并不重要。
What matters is the process.
重要的是过程。
Don’t you want to wait until you are 70 or 80 years old?
难道你不想等到 70、80岁，
Did you fall in love when you were old?
你老的时候恋爱过吗？
It felt like mom wanted sex.
感觉就像妈妈想要做爱。
what are you saying?
你在说什么？
Brother Lan.
兰兄。
You don’t feel that much of a burden.
你不觉得有那么大的负担。
I have no opinion.
我没有意见。
I'm just an ordinary person, I don't want to talk anymore
我就是个普通人， 不想说话了
I really don't have time.
我真的没有时间。
Young boss.
年轻的老板。
We have two weeks left in our charity work
我们的慈善工作还剩两周
will expire.
将会过期。
All these explanatory documents,
所有这些解释性文件，
Please fill in quickly
请快速填写
The hospital asked,
医院询问，
we want to apply
我们想申请
Continue to perform medical assistance missions next year
明年继续执行医疗援助任务
Or want to go back to China?
或者想回中国？
Anything else?
还有别的事吗？
The infirmary also asked me to remind you,
医务室还 让我提醒你，
Before the crew came to Lakaya on a rescue mission,
在船员们来到 拉卡亚执行救援任务之前，
On the stalled glioma program.
关于停滞不前的神经胶质瘤项目。
After He Xiaoguang took over,
何晓光接任后，
Still no progress.
仍然没有进展。
If this situation continues,
如果这种情况持续下去，
You will not be able to apply for scientific research funding for the next year.
则不能再申请 下一年度的科研经费。
The other one is about the Young Talents Program.
另外一个是关于青年英才计划的，
Held every four years.
每四年举行一次。
if you don't come back
如果你不回来的话
It is very likely that it will be taken away by He Xiaogong.
很有可能会被 何小贡拿走。
So now do we want to go back or not?
那么现在 我们到底想回去还是不想回去呢？
Young boss.
年轻的老板。
if we go back to china
如果我们回到中国
What will happen between you and Wei An ?
你和维安之间会发生什么 ？
you two,
你们俩，
Have you confirmed the relationship?
已经确认关系了吗？
If you return to China,
如果你回到中国，
Will he come or not?
他会来还是不来？
Jiang Muying asked you to ask?
江暮影让你问的？
I...I'm just worried.
我……我只是担心。
You're too busy pretending that your leg isn't healed yet
你正忙着假装 你的腿还没有痊愈
It's also difficult
也很难
correct?
正确的？
Isn't my leg healed yet?
我的腿还没痊愈吗？
Look at my beautiful legs.
你看看我美丽的腿。
I'm just kidding.
我只是在开玩笑。
Your legs haven't healed yet, so don't move them too much.
你的腿还没痊愈， 别动太多。
It doesn't matter.
没关系。
Still sick?
还病着吗？
It hurts, really hurts.
很痛，真的很痛。
it does not matter.
这没关系。
Recently,
这几天，
you can have surgery
你可以做手术
Why is it still so bad?
为什么还是这么糟糕？
You can sit near the operating table,
可以坐在手术台附近，
So my legs won't be affected too much.
所以我的腿不会 受到太大影响。
why are you laughing?
你笑什么？
Fang Mingfan.
Fang Mingfan.
Don't you have an emergency?
你没有紧急情况吗？
When is my time...
我的时间什么时候...
that's right.
这是正确的。
I have an emergency.
我有紧急情况。
Look at the young boss.
请看年轻的老板。
[Gu Yunzheng]
[Gu Yunzheng]
Surgery can still be performed,
仍可进行手术，
It seems that your problem is not serious.
看来你的问题不是很严重。
Take a break.
休息一下吧。
wait.
等待。
After taking my white coat, do you want to leave?
拿了我的白大褂之后， 你就想走吗？
The lounge is too cold, I...
休息室太冷了，我...
Just be careless.
不小心就可以了。
Did you just take it away accidentally?
就这么不小心就拿走了吗？
My legs hurt because of you.
我的腿因为你而疼痛。
Do you want to pretend you don't know?
你想假装不知道吗？
After that, what more do you want?
之后，你还想要什么？
You must have studied in college,
你一定在大学期间学习过，
In human saliva,
在人类唾液中，
There is something called opiorphin.
有一种东西 叫opiorphin。
this material
这种材料
Has analgesic effects comparable to morphine .
具有与吗啡相当的镇痛作用 。
this means,
这意味着，
Direct kissing can help relieve pain.
直接接吻可以 帮助缓解疼痛。
If you live long you can see anything.
如果你活得长久， 你就能看到任何东西。
Unexpectedly, this noble and cold little boss
没想到这个高贵冷酷的小老板
One day you will be rejected.
有一天会被拒绝。
Are you really bored?
你真的很无聊吗？
Do you want to take care of the emergency department for a week straight?
您想连续照顾急诊科 一周吗？
sorry for interrupting you.
对不起，打扰您了。
♪Love requires honesty♪
♪爱情需要诚实♪
Please do not make loud noises in the hospital.
请勿在医院内大声喧哗。
Quiet.
安静。
[Jinhai City]
[金海城]
[Wen Ran]
[Wen Ran]
Yuncheng.
运城。
My father invites you to his house for dinner on the weekend
我父亲 周末邀请你去他家吃饭
What do you want to eat?
你想吃什么？
I can prepare the materials first
我可以先准备好材料
Or we can go to the supermarket together.
或者我们可以 一起去超市。
I really enjoy going to the supermarket with you.
我真的很喜欢 和你一起去超市。
[I want to go abroad, so I can’t come this weekend. 】
【我要出国，所以 这个周末不能来。】
Enter.
进入。
Director Du.
杜导演.
Have you booked the flight to Lakaya that I asked you to book?
我让你订的去拉卡亚的机票你 订好了吗？
Oh yeah.
哦耶。
But I have something to report.
但我有件事 要报告。
speak out.
说出来。
Phase III clinical trial of HDQ39
HDQ39的III期临床试验
Started
已开始
In order to increase the stock price,
考虑到 提升股价，
The Steering Committee would like to take this opportunity to hold a media conference.
指导委员会谨借此机会 举行一次媒体会议。
Please sir, can you attend.
请先生可以参加。
I held a press conference when I came back.
我回来后召开新闻发布会。
Recruitment will begin next week.
招聘将于下周开始。
If you wait until later...
如果你等到稍后回来的话...
for me.
为我。
How committed are you to this project?
您 对这个项目的投入程度如何？
The decision of the Board of Directors will be determined .
将决定 董事会的决定。
If you can attend the press conference in person,
如果您本人能参加 新闻发布会，
The next phase of the financing process will be smoother.
下一阶段融资进程 将会更加顺利。
That's it, please cancel my ticket.
就是这样，请 取消我的机票。
OK
好的。
【Friendly Hospital】 【Lakaya】
【友好医院】 【拉卡亚】
[Fang Mingfan] (Tapi sekarang, disebabkan Su Wei'an,)
[Fang Mingfan] (Tapi sekarang, disebabkan Su Wei'an,)
(He changed his mind again.)
（他又改变主意了。）
(Hesitates a little,)
（稍微犹豫一下，）
(I'll ask for more information later.)
（稍后我会询问更多信息。）
[Gu Yunzheng]
[Gu Yunzheng]
What to look at?
看看什么？
River,
江，
Among the beauty products you own ,
在您拥有的美容产品中 ，
Are there any products that can brighten skin tone?
有没有什么产品 可以提亮肤色？
Why do you suddenly want to brighten your skin tone?
为什么突然 想提亮肤色？
Didn't you always dislike me before?
以前不是你一直不喜欢我吗？
Because I've been taking care of my skin?
因为我一直在照顾我的皮肤？
Women beautify themselves for the person they like.
女人 为了自己喜欢的人而美丽自己。
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
Awak dan Gu Yunzheng
Awak dan Gu Yunzheng
do what
做什么
Two days and one night in the jungle ?
在丛林中度过两天 一夜？
Didn't do anything.
没有做任何事情。
Right time, right place, right person. Everything is done.
对的时间，对的地点， 对的人。一切都完成了。
I didn't expect you to seduce Gu Yunzheng.
我没想到你能 勾引顾云峥。
Romantic drama turns into a night of wilderness survival .
浪漫的戏剧变成了荒野生存的夜晚 。
It's just a waste of fate,
只是浪费了命运，
Be prepared for thunderstorms.
为雷暴做好准备。
No. What do you think about every day?
不，你每天都在想什么？
Why do things happen between us?
为什么 我们之间会发生一些事情？
Sister, I'm worried about you.
姐姐，我很担心你。
If they don't seize this opportunity, they will want to return to China.
如果再不抓住这个机会， 他们就想回中国了。
Go back to China?
回中国？
Why?
为什么？
Fang Mingfan kata,
Fang Mingfan kata,
Their medical assistance mission is coming to an end.
他们的医疗援助任务 即将结束。
So they will come back after that .
所以他们在那之后会回来 。
Didn't Gu Yunzheng tell you?
顾云铮没告诉你吗？
it should be.
它应该是。
After all, you two
毕竟你们两个
not together
不在一起
Although Kampong Rabe has such a good opportunity.
尽管甘榜拉贝有这么好的机会。
I think,
我觉得，
He thinks you have no heart for him.
他认为你对他没有心。
So he doesn't dare to take you back to China.
所以他不敢 带你一起回中国。
I really don't understand you.
我真的不明白你。
you say. He is tall and handsome.
你说。 他又高又帅了。
He is also the person you liked before .
他也是你以前喜欢的人 。
He is right in front of you,
他就在你眼前，
You just let him go?
你就让他走了？
I really hope,
我真心希望，
For example, tomorrow is Judgment Day,
例如，明天是审判日，
This world is destroyed,
这个世界毁灭了，
I still want to have a great relationship.
我仍然想拥有 一段美好的爱情关系。
If not, it's really a loss.
如果没有，那就真的是损失了。
I want to go back to China and he is still so close to me.
我想回中国， 他还离我那么近。
What does it mean?
这是什么意思？
How are you, have you ever thought about cooking?
你好吗，有想过做饭吗？
Where do we want to go?
我们想去哪里？
Keep moving.
继续移动。
You don't want to kidnap me, do you?
你不会想绑架我吧？
Have you seen the kidnapper sitting in the passenger seat?
你见过绑匪坐在乘客座位上吗
And let the hostages take the car?
并让人质劫走汽车？
your leg is hurt
你的腿受伤了
You were supposed to go to the hospital to rest, but you insisted on going out.
本来应该去医院休息的， 你却非要出去。
Prepare to ask me to drive for you again .
准备再次请我 为你开车。
Didn't you let me use your car?
不是你让 我用你的车的吗？
Do you want to get money?
你想得到钱吗？
son.
儿子。
So where exactly are we going?
那么我们到底要去哪里呢？
I heard a story about a local tribe
我听说过一个 关于当地部落的故事
There is a reliable shaman,
有一个可靠的萨满，
Experts in the treatment of difficult and complicated diseases.
治疗 疑难杂症的专家。
I want to go out there and get my legs checked out.
我想去那里 检查一下我的腿。
What?
什么？
You are an associate professor at Huaren University.
您是华仁大学的副教授。
Can you respect science?
你能尊重一下科学吗？
According to today’s modern medicine,
根据今天的现代医学，
My leg pain should be gone.
我的腿痛 应该已经好了。
But the problem now is that he hasn't recovered yet.
但现在的问题 是，他还没有恢复过来。
I felt an evil energy entering my body.
我感觉有一股邪恶的能量 进入体内。
So if you follow,
所以如果你遵循，
This is something that modern medicine cannot explain.
这是现代医学无法解释的。
Therefore, we need to find another way.
所以，需要另想办法。
Go all the way to the end and turn right.
一直走到尽头， 然后右转。
As I said before, the fare is doubled.
我之前说过， 车费加倍。
Great, no problem.
很好，没问题。
Is this the shaman's house you're talking about?
这就是你说的萨满的房子吗？
Yes, it's a bit unique.
是的，它有点独特。
Did he go outside for treatment?
他去外面治病了啊？
look,
你看，
Navigation brought me here.
导航把我带到了这里。
OK
好的。
I also want to find a shaman
我也想找个萨满
Open a branch here.
在这里开设分店。
Mesra Hospital Untreatable Diseases,
梅斯拉医院 无法治疗的疾病，
Asking for help Dr. Gu brought them here yes.
寻求帮助博士。顾 带他们来这里是的。
You will definitely be able to make a lot of profits.
一定能够赚取大量的利润。
I have no idea,
我不知道，
This tree has a soul.
这棵树有灵魂。
you do not say,
你不说，
my leg
我的这条腿
I no longer feel pain. Look at this.
我不再感到疼痛了。 你看看这个。
hurry up.
快点。
I'll take you to a place.
我带你去一个地方。
Look at that.
看那个。
really beautiful!
真的很美！
This bridge was built by the Chinese.
这座桥是中国人建造的。
I have been in Lakaya for more than a year
我来 拉卡亚一年多了
I have passed through so many bridges built by the Chinese.
走过了那么 多中国人修建的桥梁。
Every time I think like this,
每次这样想的时候，
In all this there is not one or the other
在这一切之中， 没有一个或另一个
Built by my mom.
由我妈妈建造的。
Of course there is.
当然有。
Your mother is a respectable woman.
你的母亲是 一个值得尊敬的女人。
that's right.
这是正确的。
if she wasn't my mother
如果她不是我妈妈
perhaps
或许
i will love him
我会爱他
Let's ask him how he is.
我们来问问他怎么样吧。
Hello!
喂！
Are you OK?
你好吗？
Is this a replica bridge?
这是一座复制桥吗？
It is said that a light festival is held here every year.
据说 这里每年都会举办灯光节。
It’s just that I’ve lived in Lakaya for so long,
只是我在拉卡亚生活了这么久，
There is no chance to join yet.
目前还没有机会加入。
that's right.
这是正确的。
Maybe it's because you are too busy looking for money.
也许是因为你 太忙于找钱了。
You ran so fast just now,
刚才你跑得那么快，
Are your legs no longer sore?
你的腿不再酸痛了吗？
sick. Still uncomfortable.
生病的。仍然不舒服。
Do you want to try it?
你想尝试一下吗？
Nothing wrong?
没有什么不对吗？
I tell you,
我告诉你，
This game releases the hormone dopamine in us,
这场比赛可以 让我们释放多巴胺激素，
let's get excited
让我们兴奋
The same goes for having sex.
做爱也一样。
It seems that I am more effective than the shaman.
看来我 比萨满还有效。
Your leg seems to be healed.
你的腿似乎 已经痊愈了。
Pay.
支付。
Why?
为什么？
The hostage demands money from the kidnapper.
人质 向绑匪索要钱财。
You look more like a hostage than me .
你看起来比我更像人质 。
If you want money, there isn't any.
如果你要钱，也没有。
If you want this person, you can change it to yours.
如果你想要这个人， 你可以把它改成你的。
What did you say?
你说什么？
I didn't hear it.
我没听见。
You stopped performing again.
你又停止 表演了。
Didn't you hear?
你没听见吗？
You guessed it.
你猜到了。
We are dizzy again.
我们又头晕了。
hurry up!
赶快！
Suddenly out of nowhere,
突然不知从何而来，
When will this all be available?
当这一切都可用时？
That day was mountain time,
那天是山上的时间，
I'm hungry, thirsty, and scared.
我又饿又渴， 我害怕。
So I prepared a little earlier this time.
所以这次 准备得早了一些。
Be prepared for any eventuality?
准备好应对任何可能发生的情况吧？
this thing
这东西
Essential for outdoor survival.
户外生存所必需的。
Is this also important for surviving outside?
这对于 在外面生存也很重要？
You shouldn't underestimate this picnic mat.
你不应该小看 这个野餐垫。
It is moisture-proof, waterproof and wear-resistant.
它防潮、防水 、耐磨。
This is a must-have item
这是必备单品
Go travel.
去旅行。
brother,
兄弟，
We are in the desert now .
我们现在 在沙漠里。
You talked to me about waterproofing and moisture-proofing.
你跟我 谈到防水防潮。
Be prepared for any eventuality?
准备好应对任何可能发生的情况吧？
This one too?
这个也是？
Do you remember our time in the mountains?
你还记得我们在山里的时光吗
Our cell phones are running out of battery, right?
我们的手机都快 没电了，对吧？
This type of battery will last longer. look.
这种类型的电池会 持续更长时间。你看。
oh.
哦。
So what you mean is,
所以你的意思是，
We'll hang it on ourselves later
稍后我们会把它挂在身上
For lighting?
用于照明？
You can hang it high.
你可以把它挂 在高处。
Try looking at it this way.
你试着这样看。
It would look beautiful if hung on a tent.
如果把它挂在帐篷上，一定很漂亮。
tent?
帐篷？
Are you ready to bring your tent?
你准备好带帐篷了吗？
Wei An, are you thirsty?
维安，你渴吗？
I saw you finished your drink.
我看到你 把酒喝完了。
no.
不是。
where is my water
我的水在哪里
Who turned it into alcohol?
谁把它变成了酒精？
no.
不是。
(Alcohol gives people courage.)
（酒精给人勇气。）
(You two are cowards.)
（你们两个都是胆小鬼。）
(I can only help so far.)
（我只能提供到目前为止的帮助。）
【Friendly Hospital】
【友好医院】
Obviously,
显然，
Only drink.
只能喝酒。
Quench your thirst.
解渴。
Have some wine to quench your thirst.
喝点酒解渴。
Very comfortable.
很舒服。
It feels like a long time ago
感觉像是很久以前的事
Not enjoying the tranquility of the night
不享受夜晚的宁静
comfortably.
舒适地。
No need to think about anything.
无需考虑任何事情。
Just need to be quiet
只需要安静
Enjoy the beauty of the night sky.
欣赏夜空的美丽。
me too.
我也一样。
I used to do this every day
以前我每天都这样做
Busy as a machine.
像机器一样忙碌。
But never stop and think for a moment
但永远不要 停下来思考片刻
What do I work for?
我工作是为了什么？
Oh yes.
哦是的。
I've finished the wine and can't go back.
酒已经喝完了， 不能再回去了。
Don't worry.
不用担心。
As long as I'm here, you're safe.
只要我在， 你就安全。
However, I also think that
但是，我也认为，
You are the source of danger.
你就是危险的根源。
Do you think I 've reached that point?
你认为我 已经到了那个地步了吗？
Although I love you,
尽管我爱你，
I won't take advantage of you either.
我也不会占你的便宜。
But I will.
但我会。
What did you say?
你说什么？
No.
不。
OK
好的。
you are great too.
你也很棒。
must be.
必须是。
Taste it first.
先尝尝。
odor.
气味。
use this.
用这个。
No, I'm not cold either.
不用了，我也不冷。
Drinking alcohol can warm the body.
饮酒可以温暖身体。
OK
好的。
Hurry up and give it a try.
快点尝试一下吧。
let's go
我们走吧
Cheers to beauty tonight.
今晚为美丽干杯。
OK
好的。
drink!
喝！
Why do we fight?
我们为什么打架？
The winner may make one request.
获胜者可以提出一项请求。
Against what?
反对什么？
Opponents look for zodiac signs.
反对者寻找十二生肖星座。
Whoever can find the most people wins.
谁能找到最多的人就 获胜。
how?
如何？
I was in an astronomy club in college.
我在大学时曾参加过天文俱乐部。
Do you really want to fight me?
你真的想 和我战斗吗？
Is it really great?
真的很棒吗？
I once took a tour group to the desert.
我曾经带过 一个旅游团去沙漠。
Clients taught me and I also learned Chinese and French.
客户教过我， 我也学过中文和法语。
Are these hearsays of yours credible?
你的这些道听途说 可信吗？
Believe it or not, your opponent knows first.
信不信由 对手先知道。
Why?
为什么？
Or do you think that lecturers lose to students?
或者你认为 讲师输给了学生，
Is your face watering?
你的脸流水了吗？
Classmate Su.
苏同学。
What kind of strange desire to win is this?
你这到底是一种什么奇怪的求胜欲望啊？
Let's get in the car and go fight.
我们坐上车 去战斗吧。
Bintang Orion.
宾唐猎户座。
how is it like?
什么样的？
do you know?
你知道吗？
Betelgeuse is a star
参宿四是一颗恒星
Bright orange, a thousand times larger than the sun.
明亮的橙色，大小 比太阳大一千倍。
Betelgeuse...
参宿四...
The stars of Ursa Major and Ursa Minor.
大熊座星、小熊座星。
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
Do you really want to fight?
你真的想打架吗？
Aren't you afraid of losing and crying behind you?
就不怕输到 后面哭吗？
If you haven't started looking yet,
如果你还没有开始寻找，
You will definitely lose.
你一定会输。
OK
好的。
Now that I can find those two stars,
既然我能找到 那两颗星星，
Not hard to find...
不难找到...
Draco star.
德拉科星.
Cassiopeia star.
仙后座星。
Gemini, Auriga.
双子星、御夫座星。
Auriga?
御夫星？
of.
的。
Did you come up with this name?
这个名字是你想出来的吗？
Why should I create?
我为什么还要创造？
Skilled driver.
熟练的车夫。
Where? Let me get closer.
在哪里？让我靠近一下。
Situ.
司徒。
Have you seen the brightest star?
你看到 最亮的星星了吗？
Its name is Capella,
它的名字叫卡佩拉，
It is one of the main stars in the constellation Auriga.
它是御夫座的主要恒星之一。
A lonely star.
一颗孤独的星星。
what you see is
你看到的是
A pair of major stars.
一对主要明星。
They are a pair of twin stars.
他们是一对双星。
They are very close together in orbit .
它们在轨道上的距离 非常近。
They revolve around the same center of mass.
彼此 围绕同一质心公转。
it mean,
它的意思是，
They are not alone.
他们并不孤单。
I said four stars before.
之前我说过四星。
You just said three, so I win.
你刚才说的是三，所以我赢了。
Where could that be?
那会是哪里呢？
I haven't finished speaking yet.
我话还没说完。
Did you say that?
你这么说了吗？
winner...
优胜者...
♪Death Dialogue♪
♪死亡对话♪
♪Innocent words♪
♪天真的话语♪
♪My eyes are falling♪
♪眼睛掉下来了♪
♪The warmth that enters the palm of your hand...♪
♪进入你手掌的温暖...♪
Already admitted it.
就已经承认了。
♪Heartbeat speeds up♪
♪心跳加速♪
♪Shrouded in nightmares...♪
♪被噩梦笼罩...♪
lose to you,
输给你，
I do.
我愿意。
♪Pelukan selamatkanku♪
♪Pelukan selamatkanku♪
♪Rashisham♪
♪拉希夏姆♪
♪I listen to every word of your dream♪
♪我聆听你梦想的每一个字♪
♪Secretly record laughter♪
♪偷偷记录笑声♪
♪Segala impianmu♪
♪Segala impianmu♪
♪Rashaku♪
♪拉夏库♪
♪I forgot that I was once a desert island♪
♪我忘了 我曾经是一座荒岛♪
♪I miss you for waiting so long♪
♪我想念 你等了这么久♪
♪ Tariq Bajuku ♪
♪塔里克巴茹库♪
♪Aku Sintamu♪
♪阿库辛塔穆♪
are you awake
你醒着么
Stop pretending, I've seen it.
别再装了， 我已经看到了。
Its daybreak.
天亮了。
Did you sleep well last night?
你昨晚睡的好吗？
Not too good, I feel like I’m going to sleep again.
不太好，感觉又要睡觉了。
Which part is bad?
哪个部分不好？
I can try again.
我可以再试一次。
Good, it's time to wake up.
很好，已经可以醒来了。
Wei'an,
Wei'an,
I want to hug you like this every day.
我想 每天都这样拥抱你。
Medical rescue mission ends
医疗救助任务结束
Hospital
医院
Will tell me to come back as soon as possible.
会告诉我尽快回来。
♪At night, turn the hands of the clock♪
♪晚上，转动时钟指针♪
♪Noise is replacing silence♪
♪噪音正在取代沉默♪
♪We act out the meeting script♪
♪我们表演会议剧本♪
♪The rainbow that decorates the night♪
♪装饰夜晚的彩虹♪
♪And the wind that passes through the desert♪
♪还有穿过沙漠的风♪
♪Have been our witnesses♪
♪曾经是我们的见证者♪
♪We are all people lost in obscurity♪
♪我们都是迷失 在默默无闻中的人♪
♪Find one out of a billion possibilities♪
♪从十亿种可能性中找出一种♪
♪Trapped in a city called destiny ♪
♪被困在名为命运的都市 ♪
♪But still chasing stars♪
♪但还是追星♪
♪Don’t worry my beloved wanderer♪
♪别担心 我心爱的流浪者♪
♪Hold a glass of wine to warm your lonely soul♪
♪捧一杯酒 ，温暖孤独的心灵♪
♪Let me hug your crack♪
♪让我拥抱你的裂缝♪
♪You are as bright as a star♪
♪你像星星一样明亮♪
♪Twinkle in the silence♪
♪在寂静中闪烁♪
♪At night, turn the hands of the clock♪
♪晚上，转动时钟指针♪
♪Noise is replacing silence♪
♪噪音正在取代沉默♪
♪We act out the meeting script♪
♪我们表演会议剧本♪
♪The rainbow that decorates the night♪
♪装饰夜晚的彩虹♪
♪And the wind that passes through the desert♪
♪还有穿过沙漠的风♪
♪Have been our witnesses♪
♪曾经是我们的见证者♪
♪We are all people lost in obscurity♪
♪我们都是迷失 在默默无闻中的人♪
♪Find one out of a billion possibilities♪
♪从十亿种可能性中找出一种♪
♪Trapped in a city called destiny ♪
♪被困在名为命运的都市 ♪
♪But still chasing stars♪
♪但还是追星♪
♪Don’t worry my beloved wanderer♪
♪别担心 我心爱的流浪者♪
♪Hold a glass of wine to warm your lonely soul♪
♪捧一杯酒 ，温暖孤独的心灵♪
♪Let me hug your crack♪
♪让我拥抱你的裂缝♪
♪You are as bright as a star♪
♪你像星星一样明亮♪
♪Twinkle in the silence♪
♪在寂静中闪烁♪